<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Great St. Marie's church in Cambridge before the Right Honourable the Lord Chief-Justice Holt, at the assizes held there, August 1, 1693 / by Tho. Walker ...</title>
            <author>Walker, Thomas, 1658 or 9-1716.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67269</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W416</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4995</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12021310</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12021310</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52620</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67269)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52620)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 882:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Great St. Marie's church in Cambridge before the Right Honourable the Lord Chief-Justice Holt, at the assizes held there, August 1, 1693 / by Tho. Walker ...</title>
                  <author>Walker, Thomas, 1658 or 9-1716.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Hayes ... for William Graves ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Cambridge :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Proverbs XII, 26 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:52620:1"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Octob.</hi> 20. 1693.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Geo. Oxenden,</hi> Procan.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo. Beaumont,</hi> S. Th. Pr.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo. Mountagu,</hi> Coll. Trin. Magiſter.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ja. Johnſon,</hi> Coll. Sid. Magiſter.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52620:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at Great S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>MARIE'S</hi> Church IN CAMBRIDGE, <hi>Before the Right Honourable</hi> The Lord Chief-Juſtice <hi>HOLT,</hi> AT THE ASSIZES Held there, <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1. 1693.</p>
            <p>By <hi>THO. WALKER</hi> B. D. Fellow of <hi>Sidney-Suſſex</hi> Coll.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <bibl>Ariſtoph. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>CAMBRIDGE,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Hayes,</hi> Printer to the Univerſity, For <hi>William Graves</hi> Bookſeller there. 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:52620:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52620:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>JOHN HOLT,</hi> Lord Chief-Juſtice OF THE KING'S BENCH, And One of Their MAJESTIES <hi>Moſt Honourable</hi> PRIVY COUNCIL.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I lately had the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Happineſs of wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon Your Lordſhip, You were pleas'd to Encourage the Publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:52620:3"/>of this Diſcourſe, in ſuch Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Terms, as I cannot here, in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, relate. Your Lordſhip's Repeated Requeſts, which to me are Equivalent to Commands, and Your Generous Prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer of giving theſe Papers Protection, being ſuch Powerfull Arguments to me, as I could not in Duty withſtand, have uſher'd them into the Publick Light. This is a ſufficient Apology to excuſe me from Arrogance and Preſumption, if there had been no other Reaſon for my appearing in Print: But whilst I was in the Country, I was not only ſurpriz'd with a Letter ſent me by an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nknown Hand, miſrepreſenting my Sermon; but ſoon after I came to the College, I was Allarm'd with the Noiſe which ſome Men had made about it, and not a little Concern'd at the Invidious miſconſtructions which they had put upon it. And therefore
<pb facs="tcp:52620:3"/>as well in my own Vindication, as in Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Your Lordſhip's Command, I ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it to a more Publick Cenſure than it has already undergone. All Men, who are Juſt and Impartial, have ſo High a Value for Your Lordſhip's Judgement, and ſo Great an Opinion of Your Candour and Integrity, that ſeeing Your Lordſhip has been pleas'd to caſt a Favourable Aſpect upon this Diſcourſe, it raiſes ſome hopes in me, that how contemptible ſoever it may ſeem in the Eyes of ſome Perſons; yet it may meet with a Candid Reception a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt others, of Your Lordſhip's Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter, who are Hearty Lovers of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> of their <hi>Majeſties,</hi> and this <hi>Nation.</hi> As for thoſe who are not, as I neither expect their Favour, ſo neither do I much regard their Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. If any are offended with my <hi>Sermon,</hi> it is their own fault and not mine. I am
<pb facs="tcp:52620:4"/>perſwaded no Honeſt Man will Vindicate the Characters of thoſe whom I undertake to expoſe. As I have ſaid nothing but what I really believe to be true, ſo I hope my Sincerity may Atone for the meanneſs of my Performance; and Your Lordſhip's Kind Acceptance of it, will, in my Eſteem, overballance the Sleights and Reproaches of thoſe who vilifie and condemn it. May your Lordſhip live many Happy Years, to Adorn the Station You deſervedly Poſſeſs, to do Juſtice, and Promote the Publick Good; and, after You have long been a Bleſſing to this Kingdom, may You be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd into that of Eternal Glory, which is the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfeigned Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your</hi> Honour's <hi>Moſt Obedient, Obliged, and Very Humble Servant,</hi> THO. WALKER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52620:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. xii. V. 26.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>The Righteous is more Excellent than his Neighbour.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT there is a real Diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Good and Evil, Virtue and Vice, which was ſo antecedently to all poſitive Laws, whether Human or Divine: and that the natural Defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, and innate Turpitude of the one, and the ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Agreeableneſs and inherent Rectitude of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do not barely depend upon the arbitrary Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thoſe who have enacted Laws concerning them, is a Truth ſo obvious, and manifeſt to any one, who duly conſiders the Nature of things, and ſoberly attends to the reaſonings and reflections of his own Mind; that one may juſtly admire how it comes to paſs, that the dull and exploded Notions of
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>egen. Laert. in Vita Ariſtip. p.</hi> 134. <hi>ed. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtel.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ariſtippus,
<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>V.</hi> Lactant. <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>de Juſtitia.</hi>
                  </note> Carneades</hi> and other Philoſophers of old, concerning theſe matters, ſhould be again, with Confidence enough, reviv'd, (eſpecially in this Thinking and Philoſophical Age) by Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> and his Followers, who pretend to a more than ordinary ſmartneſs and ſagacity in Reaſoning and Speculation. Thus He, who whilſt he lived was the Greateſt won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the <hi>Peak,</hi> in the Preface to his Book <hi>de Cive,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:52620:5"/>huggs, and applauds himſelf for having found out the great and infallible Medicine for Wounded Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences and troubled Minds: by diſpelling thoſe miſts of Error, as he calls them, in which Men, before this <hi>Phoſphorus</hi> aroſe, were involv'd, concerning Juſt and Unjuſt, Good and Evil: in having clearly demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, by ſolid Reaſons, as he vainly inſinuates, that there are no Doctrines Authentick concerning them beſide the Laws and Conſtitutions of each particular City. And in his Book <hi>de Corpore Politico,</hi> he bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and in plain terms aſſerts, that
<note n="a" place="margin">C. 1. <hi>p.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>Jus &amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tile</hi> right and profit is the ſame thing. So that, according to this Doctrine, if it ſhould happen, that two or more Cities or Nations ſhould have contrary Apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and different Sentiments concerning Good and Evil, Juſt and Unjuſt, that then theſe Creatures of Civil Power muſt ſubmit to new Names, and change their Liveries as often as they change their Maſters. But I can never believe, that theft and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, injuſtice and oppreſſion, deceit and treachery ſhould become good and laudable Qualities, by what Laws ſoever they were enacted, or by what Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſoever they ſhould be confirmed: or that, amongſt Wiſe and ſober Men, they ſhould be reputed more excellent and praiſe-worthy than Honeſty and Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, than Juſtice and Integrity, than Sincerity and Fair-Dealing in all the mutual tranſactions of our Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs. Certainly the Foundations upon which the laws and principles of Juſtice and Equity are built, are as unchangeable and immovable as the Will of God, whereby he eſtabliſhes the immutable Decrees of his Wiſdom and Goodneſs; and that we may as well ſuppoſe Men able to change the Nature of things, to turn a Spirit into a Body, or a Body into a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:52620:5"/>Spirit, as that they ſhould be able to alter and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fix thoſe ſteady Rules, whereby we take our meaſures concerning Good or Evil. The laws of the inviſible, and immaterial World are no leſs ſtable and certain than thoſe are by which we obſerve this vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Frame of things to be guided, in the producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their neceſſary Effects, and in their ſtated and conſtant courſes, and periodical Revolutions. 'Tis as unnatural and irrational to ſay, or make a law that God is not to be worſhipped, to affirm that 'tis wickedneſs and impiety to render to every one their due; or that it is ſin and folly to live ſoberly, righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly and Godly, as it would be for a Man to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to make fire and water loſe their innate Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of heat and coldneſs, by commanding them to do ſo: and that they ſhould mutually change their Properties, that Fire ſhould become naturally cold, and Water hot, whenſoever a company of Men in Authority, ſhould pretend to eſtabliſh the Abſurdity by a Law. This would be as impoſſible and impra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticable too, as that the Sun ſhould riſe in the Weſt, and take a contrary Courſe to what it hath done from the beginning of the World, when the Grand <hi>Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior</hi> pleaſes to command it, who, as I think, amongſt his other magnificent Titles, ſtiles himſelf Lord of the Sun and Moon.</p>
            <p>But farther, if there be any Advantage on either ſide, the Laws of Reaſon and of the intellectual World may fairly challenge it: for as God can never ceaſe to be Holy, Wiſe and Good, and was ſo from all Eternity, ſo theſe Emanations of eternal Wiſdom and Reaſon, can never, no not for a moment, ceaſe to be what they are: whereas the material and viſible World, having not been from Eternity, but created
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52620:6"/>in time by God, the laws by which he governs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t are changeable at his Will, and he can ſuſpend the Execution of them when he pleaſes. So he once made the
<note n="a" place="margin">Joſh. 10.12.</note> Sun to ſtand ſtill upon an extraordinary Occaſion, and reſtrained the violent Flames and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe Heat of the bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ning fiery Furnace, that it ſhould have no power to hurt the
<note n="b" place="margin">Dan. c 3.</note> Three Children who were thrown into it. But thô we read of Gods al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering the Courſe of Nature, and of his ſuſpending the Laws whereby this material World is acted and govern'd, by vertue of his Supreme Dominion and Prerogative, which are eſſential to him as Lord and Creator of all things beſide Himſelf; yet we no where read, that he ever either commanded or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed any Man to do a moral Evil; to Steal, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Murder or Adultery; to Worſhip any other Gods beſide Himſelf; or to Blaſpheme and take his Holy Name in vain <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For thô God commanded <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Gen 22</note> to ſacrifice his Son, yet even then he did not tempt him to ſin; but only made Trial of the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of his Faith and Obedience: and choſe to ſhow an extraordinary Inſtance of his Providence, by ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding an Angel to ſtay his Hands, which were ready to give the Fatal ſtroke, rather than ſuffer him to imbrue them in his own Blood, by ſhedding that of his innocent and onely Son.</p>
            <p>And although we read that God allow'd the
<note n="d" place="margin">Exod. 3.22.12.35, 36.</note> 
               <hi>Iſ. raelites,</hi> at their departure out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> to ſpeil the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> by giving them ſo much favour with their Cruel Taskmaſters, as to borrow Jewels of Silver and Jewels of Gold and Raiment of them, without paying them again; yet neither in this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, can we charge God as the Patron of Sin. For he being abſolute Lord and Proprietor of all the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52620:6"/>World, can transferr one mans Right to another when he pleaſes; but more eſpecially then, when he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feits it, by rendring himſelf obnoxious to his Divine Juſtice and Vengeance, through Oppreſſion, Fraud or Injuſtice or any other heinous Crime. But far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, this Action of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> which was appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of by God, may be accounted for after another manner; for the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> having oppreſs'd the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> for many Years, and defrauded them of their Wages, this Action, at their Departure; was onely a more Subtle way of Paying themſelves the Arrears which were due to them, and which they were in no capacity of procuring by Law, or by
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cum</hi> Hebraei <hi>diu ſervnſſent</hi> Aegyptiis, <hi>mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſque ab iis af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecti fulſſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurits, voluit De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, eis mercedem ſervitutis ſuae &amp; injariarum rependere. Id etiam notavit Auter libri Sapien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae Cap.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 17. <hi>reddens ſanctis mercedem ſanctitatis laborum ſuorum deducit eos via mirabili &amp;c.</hi> Rivet. <hi>in Cap.</hi> 12. Exod. To the ſame purpoſe <hi>Irenaeus</hi> c. 49. l. 4.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lege Naturae, quae ex ipſa deminii natura ac vi ſequitur, dupliciter fit alienatic, expletio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne juris &amp; ſucceſhone. Expletione Juris fit alienatic, quoties id quod meum nendum eſt, ſed mihi dari debet, aut lcco rei meae, aut mihi debitae, cum eam ipſam conſequi non poſſum, ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ud tantundem valens accipio, ab eo qui rem meam detinet, vel mihi debet. Nam Juſtitia expletri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> in quoties ad idem non poteſt pertingere fertur ad tantundem, quod ex merali aeſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione idem.</hi> Grot. <hi>de Jure Belii &amp; Pac. Lib</hi> 2 <hi>c.</hi> 7. <hi>V. Annot.</hi> § 2.</p>
               </note> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion.</p>
            <p>As to another Objection taken from the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Book of <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. and the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, which ſeems to encourage Inceſt, or Adultery, becauſe it is ſaid that God gave to <hi>David</hi> his Maſters Wives into his Boſom: Some ſay the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Word doth not imply <hi>Sauls.</hi> Wives, but the Maids of Honour or Attendants on the Court of <hi>Saul,</hi> out of which <hi>David</hi> might chooſe Wives: for as the
<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>B.</hi> of <hi>Werceſ.</hi> Letter to a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſt <hi>p.</hi> 127 <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tus tunc nuptiae erant, &amp; concubina etiam uxor h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den <hi>de Jure not. &amp; Gent. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 7. See more in <hi>Selden</hi> of this matter. <hi>Ambae viz.</hi> Cethura <hi>&amp;</hi> Hagar, <hi>&amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xores</hi> Abrahae <hi>&amp; Concubinae ſunt appellatae,</hi> Auguſt. <hi>de Civit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. Dei, l.</hi> 16. <hi>c.</hi> 34 <hi>v.</hi> Gen 16.3.25. 1. compared with <hi>v.</hi> 6.</note> Learned Author of the Letter to a Deiſt writes, it will be no e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſie matter, by the Conſtitution of the <hi>Moſaical</hi> Law to prove Polygamy to be Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, thô it be unlawfull now by
<note n="c" place="margin">Mat 5.32. 1 Cor. 7.4.</note> the Law of Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:52620:7"/>
            <p>So that Men can never act theſe, and ſuch like Wickedneſſes by pretending Gods Authority, when they have it not: Becauſe it cannot be that God ſhould either command, or allow them to doe a Moral evil: for if he ſhould, he muſt then be both Holy and Unholy too, to affirm which is not onely big with Contradiction, but full of Blaſphemy and Impiety. Thus as God neither can, nor will deny Himſelf, ſo neither can he nor will he, be the Author of any ſin, or the Patron of any wickedneſs; becauſe that would be to deny Himſelf, and to impeach his own Goodneſs, and Wiſdom, and Veracity, of falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and folly and weakneſs; which Imperfections are altogether repugnant to the Eſſential Holineſs of his Divine Nature.</p>
            <p>If then the Diſtinction between good and evil be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and not barely notional, and the Foundation upon which that Diſtinction is built, be ſo firm and ſtedfaſt, that it implys a Contradiction that it ſhould be altered and removed by God himſelf, it is beyond the force of any Human power to break the Golden chain of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, by which they are linked together, and to cancel the laws of Piety, Juſtice and Equity, which are of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal and immutable Obligation. For indeed, as I hinted before,
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Si populorum juſſis, ſi princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum decretis, ſi ſententiis Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, Jura con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituerentur: Jus eſſet latrcomarit Jus adulterare, Jus teſtamenta falſa ſuppenere, ſi haec ſuffragiis, aut ſcitis multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinis proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentur. atquînos legem bonam à mala nulla alia niſi naturali nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mâ dividere poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumus,</hi> Cicero <hi>de Legib. l.</hi> 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</note> if the nature of Good and Evil depended upon the capricious humours, and was to be determined by the fallible Conſtitutions of human Lawgivers; it would then be in their Power to reverſe the Face of things, when they pleas'd, and ſo in time they might quite aboliſh the Notions and Sentiments which are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted in Mens minds concerning Right and Wrong, Virtue and Vice: and the ſame Actions might paſs for Juſt and Pious at one time, which would be look'd upon to be highly Impious and Unjuſt at
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52620:7"/>another. But this can never be; for if all the World ſhould conſpire together to make it unlawfull to worſhip God, and to honour our Parents; to live Soberly, Righteouſly, and Godly: and ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to eſtabliſh a Law to make it lawfull to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Theft, Murder, or Adultery, &amp;c. it would be null and void of it ſelf, without being formally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal'd by another, and the ſame breath that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd it, would only deliver it up to the ſport and deriſion of the winds: and they who endeavour to eſtabliſh iniquity by ſuch a Law, would only ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der themſelves guilty before God, by keeping it, and would pull down upon their own Heads that Curſe denounc'd againſt them by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> c. 5. v. 20 <hi>Wo unto them that call evil good, and good evil, that put darkneſs for light, and light for darkneſs, that put bitter for ſweet, and ſweet for bitter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis the peculiar Excellence of God that he changeth not, and therefore he will never refix thoſe Laws in any time which he had decreed and eſtabliſh'd before the World began: for being infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely Wiſe, and Juſt and Good, he could not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act any Law which was either fooliſh, unjuſt, or wicked: becauſe his Knowledge, which is ſtinted by no other bounds than thoſe of Infinity and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, cannot be deceiv'd, and his Juſtice which is as eſſential to him as his very Being, would not have ſuffer'd it, and his Goodneſs, which over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpreads the whole Creation, could have took no delight and ſatisfaction in impoſing falſe notions up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Creatures, or in the reflection, and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation upon an Irregular Action in himſelf, of which he is not capable. No, he ſaw all things that He
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52620:8"/>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 1.31.</note> had <hi>made and behold they were very Good;</hi> as well in a Moral, as in a Natural reſpect: ſo that there was nothing left for the wit of Man to perform towards the Perfection of his own Nature; o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the accompliſhment of his own Happineſs, Peace, and Security even in this World: God having made ſuch ample Proviſion for him, and plac'd him in ſuch a ſtate of Perfection, that he might not only have been Happy himſelf; but alſo have deriv'd thoſe Endowments with which he was bleſt, and that Felicity which he enjoy'd, upon his Poſterity too, if he had not ſwerv'd and deviated from the Law of his Creation, in firſt willfully violating that of his Maker. For Men therefore to talk of the ſtate of Nature's being a ſtate of War, wherein all things were Lawfull, and all things Common; wherein Men were obliged by no Rules and Laws of Juſtice and Equity; but that they might, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out controul, follow the ſwing and bent of their own Vitious Inclinations and Irregular Appetites, till by conſent they tied themſelves up to be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd by certain Laws, is to reflect unworthily upon the Wiſdom and Goodneſs of God, as if Men could do better for themſelves, than either he could, or would do for them. Alas! the utmoſt we can do, cannot reſtore our lapſed Nature to its Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Integrity; or re-engrave the defaced Characters of Wiſdom and Innocence, which were once im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed on the minds of our firſt Parents, by the Finger of their all Wiſe Creator. <hi>For God created man upright, but they have ſought out many inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> Eccleſ. 7.24</p>
            <p>This then being premis'd and granted, that the nature of Good and Evil is invariable, and that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:52620:8"/>they are not the Fortuitous reſult, and offspring of Arbitrary Power and Will; but that the one is built upon the ſolid Foundation of Everlaſting Truth, and is conformable to the Will of God; and that the other is a deviation from the dictates of Right Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which is a Ray that proceeds from the Fountain of Light, and an aberration from the Divine Law.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now come to a more ſtrict diſcuſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Words of my Text. Only be pleas'd to afford your Patience, whilſt I make this Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction upon what I have ſaid: that I am ſorry we live in ſuch an Age, wherein the Prime Rules and Fundamental Principles of Religion and Morality are call'd in queſtion: wherein Men affect to be witty at the expence of their own Happineſs and Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; by endeavouring to vindicate their Enormous Crimes with a ſhew of Reaſon, which, God knows, is often as corrupt and vitiated as their Morals; and therefore it cannot but with Regret and Sorrow be reflected upon, that there ſhould be any Occaſion for Diſcourſes of this Nature.</p>
            <p>Some, alas! in this Degenerate Age, wherein down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right <hi>Atheiſm</hi> is dreſs'd up in the more plauſible Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours of <hi>Deiſm,</hi> are apt to flatter and deceive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the vain and empty Hopes, of being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Men of extraordinary Parts, and piercing Judgments, if they can but manage two or three weak and trifling Arguments againſt all Reveal'd Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: and ſo having ſhook off the Yoke that ſo ſorely gall'd them, they diſdain to be under the reſtraint and government of any other Law than what their Wild Fancies and Corrupt Imaginations
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52620:9"/>dictate to them: and ſo giving way to their Heac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrong Paſſions, and Craving Appetites, they indulge and gratifie their unruly Luſts in all the inſtances of Impiety, Lewdneſs, and Senſuality. But as ſure as there is a God that governs the World, ſo ſure hath he reveal'd his Will to Mankind, by his onely Son <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who is the <hi>Wiſdom of the Father, and the expreſs Image of his Perſon; in whom are hid all the Treaſures of Wiſdom and Knowledge;</hi> ſuch Knowledge as will make us wiſe unto Salvation, in reſpect of which all other worldly Wiſdom is but accounted Folly before God. To offer at the proof of this Point would be forreign to my Purpoſe: and therefore I return to the Handling the Words of my Text, which in the ſeveral Tranſlations of the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar <hi>Latin, Greek</hi> and <hi>Arabick,</hi> are ſo variouſly ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, that they differ as much among themſelves as they do from the Original <hi>Hebrew:</hi> to which our Tranſlation, eſpecially taking in the Marginal Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>more abundant,</hi> comes nearer than any of thoſe before mentioned, and therefore I ſhall ſtick to that, and take the Words as they fairly lye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, without offending ſome of your Ears with the uncouth and uncommon Sounds of <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Hebrew</hi> Words, which I could not avoid, if I ſhould attempt to make a Critical Diſquiſition about the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Interpretation of the Original. Having there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in what I have already ſaid, fixt the Notions of Good and Evil upon the ſolid, and immovable <hi>Baſis</hi> of Unerring and Everlaſting Truth, which I thought neceſſary to doe, to avoid a <hi>Sceptical</hi> Objection, <hi>viz.</hi> That I precariouſly begg'd the Principles I went upon, without Offering at any Proof for what
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:52620:9"/>I deliver'd: I ſhall in the following part of my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe obſerve this Method.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> I ſhall endeavour to ſhow upon what Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count <hi>a Righteous Man is more Excellent than his Neighbour,</hi> who muſt be ſuppos'd to be a Bad man; otherwiſe the Compariſon would be put in vain; for a Righteous Man would not be more Excellent than his Neighbour, if he were equally Righteous with him, and therefore the Preheminence that the One obtains above the Other, turns upon this Hinge, that the one is <hi>Righteous,</hi> and the other <hi>Wicked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I ſhall propound ſome Inſtances, wherein the <hi>Righteous Man is more Excellent than</hi> this <hi>his Neighbour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> I ſhall endeavour to ſhow upon what Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count <hi>a Righteous Man is more Excellent than his Neighbour,</hi> who is ſuppos'd to be an Ill Man: who thô he be Superior to the other in the Outward Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of this Life, in having the Advantage of a Nobler Birth, a Larger Eſtate, and a more Splendid Retinue; yet if he wants the Qualifications of a Righteous Man; if he be not Juſt and Equal in his Dealings with other Men; if he be not Moderate and Temperate in the Enjoyment of worldly Pleaſures, and piouſly and devoutly Affected towards Religion and the Service of God: a Man of meaner Quality, and more narrow Circumſtances, if he be but Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, is of a more Excellent Spirit than he, who is not ſo. Becauſe the Righteous Man more reſembles God than the other, who is the great Pattern and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52620:10"/>
               <hi>Exemplar</hi> of all that is Good, Sublime and Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent: and therefore he propounds Himſelf to out I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation, and we are commanded to be
<note n="a" place="margin">Luke 6.36.</note> 
               <hi>Mercifull</hi> becauſe our Heavenly Father is <hi>Mercifull,</hi> and to be
<note n="b" place="margin">Levit. 11.44.</note> 
               <hi>Holy</hi> becauſe he is <hi>Holy.</hi> And by how much the nearer Approaches we make towards God, in our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect Eſſays, and weak Endeavours after Holineſs and Righteouſneſs, by ſo much the more do we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble our Natures, and diſtinguiſh our ſelves more from the Plebeian Multitude, by acts of Juſtice, and Mercy and Piety, in the eſteem of the Wiſeſt and Beſt Men, than by a Numerous Attendance and Glit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Attire, which none but the injudicious Vulgar look upon as the onely diſtinguiſhing Badges of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and marks of real Worth. The Heathen <hi>Poet</hi> could diſcover the Truth of what I have ſaid, by the Light of Nature, when he expreſs'd his Sentiment in that known Diſtich,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tota licet Veteres exornent undique cerae</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Atria,</hi> Nobilitas <hi>ſola eſt at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> unica Virtus.</hi> Juv. Sat. 8.</l>
               </q> That Virtue was the ſole and true <hi>Nobility:</hi> which really raiſes one Man above another, more than all the external Advantages of Birth or Fortune naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſidered, without the Forementioned Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Righteouſneſs and Holineſs: but when they are joyned together, they then illuſtrate one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and Virtue is better able to exert it ſelf, and appears more amiable, having the Advantage of a comely Body, and proſperous Condition to ſupport it, and ſet it off. So true is it what the
<note n="c" place="margin">Greatneſs of Mind promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity <hi>p.</hi> 9.</note> H. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Boyl</hi> obſerves, that all that outward Greatneſs can doe,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52620:10"/>is not to make a Soul Great, but to afford one that is, the opportunity of ſhewing it ſelf to be ſo. <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinus quos inquinat aequat,</hi> that Wickedneſs which pollutes men makes them equal, thô their exteriour Conditions be vaſtly different and unequal.</p>
            <p>The mind of every Man is truly himſelf, and by how much that improves in Virtue and uſefull Knowledge, by ſo much doth it excell it ſelf, and thoſe of other Men, which are not imbued with the Rare endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Piety, Juſtice, and Integrity, and an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Good-will towards all Men. Suppoſe a man encompaſs'd with all the external Felicity that this World affords, poſſeſs'd of a large eſtate, and grac'd with Titles of Honour ſutable unto it; yet if his Mind be ſunk below all that is truly Noble and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous; if it be overrun and canker'd with the Ruſt of Covetouſneſs, and ſharpned with the Keenneſs of Revenge; if it be fretted and gall'd with Envy and Malice, and inflam'd with Luſt and Intemperance; if it be ſwoln and bloated with Haughtineſs and Pride, and haraſs'd with wicked Plots, and baſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns; if it be grown ſo ſavage as to delight it ſelf in ſucking the Blood of the Innocent, and in glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it ſelf with Cruelty and Oppreſſion: the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Man, thô he wants ſome of thoſe unneceſſary Superfluities which the other enjoys; but yet exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes himſelf in the conſtant Practice of the oppoſite Virtues: who endeavours to <hi>keep a Conſcience void of Offence both toward God and toward Man;</hi> who is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate in his Deſires and Enjoyments of the Good things of this Life, and kind and beneficent to thoſe whom he is concern'd to aſſiſt and relieve; who is
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52620:11"/>Juſt in his Dealings, and Faithfull to his Promiſes; who is humble and obedient to his Superiours, and Governours, civil and obliging to his Equals, and Courteous and Condeſcending to thoſe that are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him: who endeavours to relieve the Oppreſſed, and to reſcue the Innocent from the Snares of the cruel Hunter, this Man is more Excellent than the other: he will find favour with God, and be high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſteemed by all Good Men, he will be comforted and delighted with the continual Applauſe of a good Conſcience, and with the Joys of a ſerene and cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Mind. This Man is a true Subject of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, which according to the
<note place="margin">2 Rom. 14.18.</note> Apoſtle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth <hi>not in Meat and Drink,</hi> in the outward afflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Riches and Honour, but <hi>in Righteouſneſs and Peace and Joy in the Holy Ghoſt: for he in theſe things ſerveth Chriſt, is acceptable to and approved of Men.</hi> Whileſt the other, who is not endowed with the Heavenly Virtues before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, will be ſlighted and contemn'd, and onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verenc'd out of Fear, if he happen to be Great and Powerfull: for he being a Friend to no man, none will be a Friend to him, in vindicating his Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by endeavouring to wipe off the Blots, and Stains with which his Name is cover'd, by a molli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying and candid Interpretation of his Actions.</p>
            <p n="2">2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>, <hi>The Righteous Man is more Excellent than his Neighbour,</hi> becauſe he is not only reſpected by Men; but likewiſe honoured by God himſelf, who has declar'd that they who
<note n="b" place="margin">1 Sam. 2.30.</note> 
               <hi>honour him he will honour;</hi> and that he being Righteous
<note n="c" place="margin">Prov. 15.5. Pſal. 11. v. 7.</note> loveth Righteouſneſs in us, and that his eyes will behold
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52620:11"/>the Juſt with Complacency and Delight. Now there is nothing wherein we can honour God ſo much, as by endeavouring to imitate the Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and other Attributes of his Divine Nature; wherein they are imitable by us: and by doing our beſt endeavour to tranſcribe that Copy which he has ſet us, of doing Juſtice and loving Mercy, of being kind and charitable to all Men, even to the Ungratefull, and of diffuſing our good will to thoſe whom our Bounty cannot reach. We never read that God has commanded us to be <hi>Omniſcient</hi> or <hi>Omnipotent;</hi> becauſe the Attainment of theſe Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime Excellencies, and peculiar Perfections of the <hi>God-head,</hi> is plac'd beyond the Sphere and Capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of our weak and finite Natures and Abilities. But, as if we had a ſort of Infinity aſcrib'd to us in this reſpect, God has commanded us to be Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull and Holy, as he is ſo, <hi>i.e.</hi> according to the meaſure and proportion of our ſtinted Capacity, and our frail and lapſed Condition. Which we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be without firſt being Juſt, and Upright in Heart: becauſe Juſtice is a Virtue of the Firſt Magnitude, and is of ſo comprehenſive a Nature, as that it is ſaid to contain all other Virtues in its Fruitfull Womb. For indeed the love of God, and of our Neighbour, which, as we are aſſur'd by an Infallible Author, is the ſum and ſubſtance of the whole Law, is the Natural Reſult and Proper Effect of
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Primum Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiae officium eſt Deum cogneſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ut parentem, eùmqae metue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ut Dominum, diligere ut pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem. Secundum Juſtitiae officium eſt hominem ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcere velut fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem.</hi> Lactant. Epit. p. 685. Ed. Oxon.</note> Juſtice and Gratitude. For how can we abſolve our ſelves from the nonperformance of theſe Duties, without being highly Unjuſt and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull? If after having been obliged by God, in ſo Extraordinary a manner, in his giving us a being,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:52620:12"/>and providing a comfortable ſubſiſtance for us in this World, and in taking care for our Future Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, we ſhould refuſe to pay him the inconſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Tribute and Homage of our Love and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, no Name of Reproach can be bad enough for us, except it be thoſe of being Unjuſt and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull. And as Men are not ſelf-ſufficient, or able to make themſelves Happy like God, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templating and reflecting upon their own Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; and ſo wanting the help of others, are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally inclin'd to Society, from which they expect Relief and Comfort in all their Troubles and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, ſo can <hi>They</hi> by no means eſcape the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of Injuſtice, who do not lend a mutual aſſiſtance to others in their Afflictions and Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, from whom they themſelves expected and perhaps received Kindneſs and Benevolence when they labour'd under the ſame or ſuch like Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies or Diſaſters.
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Omnium, quae in docterum ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione verſantur, nibil eſt prefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctò praeſtabiliue, quàm planè in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligi nos ad Juſtitiā eſſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos; Neque opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nione; ſed natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra conſtitutum eſſe Jus.</hi> M. Tull. lib. 1. de leg. p. 326. Ed. Lamb.</note> For to that end were they born, and not for themſelves alone, according to that wiſe ſaying of <hi>Tully:</hi> of all thoſe things which are diſputed on by Learned Men, there is nothing better than plainly to underſtand, that we are born to do Juſtice, and that Right is the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Nature, and not of Opinion. Hence it is that the Law
<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 7.12.</note> 
               <hi>of doing to others as we would they ſhould do unto us again,</hi> has obtain'd ſo much credit in the World; that thô the practice of it be often neglected; yet it is every where, and by all Men commended to be moſt Juſt and Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; being taken in a right ſenſe with ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrictions and Limitations: as that our Will muſt be ſuppos'd to be Regular, and to deſire nothing
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:52620:12"/>of others, which may infringe the Laws of Equity, Modeſty, Decency, and good Manners. For if one ſhould tempt another to Lewdneſs, and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſty; to be partaker with him or her in Theft or Adultery; and ſhould make uſe of an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment grounded upon this Text, that he deſires no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of another but what he ſhould be willing to Gratifie him, or her in again, upon a like occaſion, this would be to abuſe the Rule before us; which is never ſo to be underſtood, as to patronize Sin, or elude the Laws of Juſtice, and the Precepts of Holineſs.</p>
            <p>Or, if a <hi>Criminal</hi> ſtanding at the Bar, convict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of ſome Notorious Crimes, which deſerve that the Sentence of Death ſhould be paſt upon him, ſhould argue thus: That if the Judge was in his caſe, he would willingly be acquitted, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that he ought not to paſs Sentence upon him: becauſe if he does, he violates the Rule of doing to others as he would they ſhould do unto him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain: In this Caſe a Judge ought not to take his Meaſures from the Irregularity of anothers will, but from the Rules of Juſtice and Equity, which all Men are univerſally obliged to obſerve; thô not always in their utmoſt rigour and extent. For we are adviſed by the wiſe Man,
<note n="a" place="margin">Eccleſ 7.16.</note> 
               <hi>not to be righteous over much:</hi> that is, not to ſtretch things beyond their due meaſure, and make more of a Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, or an Evidence than they will naturally and fairly bear; but to mix Clemency and Mercy with our Juſtice, and that where Right and Property,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:52620:13"/>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Platon. <hi>Protag. p.</hi> 225. <hi>Ed. Marſil. Ficin.</hi>
               </note> Peace and Safety, and the Publick Good, can be preſerv'd, and ſecur'd without inflicting Puniſhment, then to preſer Mercy before Juſtice; becauſe it is the Attribute of God we moſt Admire and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore and which is ſaid <hi>to
<note n="b" place="margin">Jam. 2.13.</note> Rejoyce,</hi> or Triumph <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Juſtice,</hi> or againſt Judgement</p>
            <p n="2">2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>, I come now to propound ſome inſtances, where in a Righteous Man excells his Neighbour.</p>
            <p>Firſt, If he be a Perſon who is entruſted with Rule and Authority, and the Adminiſtration of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: if he be Advanc'd to ſome Eminent Station either in <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>State,</hi> He prefers the <hi>Publick Good</hi> before his own <hi>Private Intereſt.</hi> He aims not at carrying on any baſe Deſigns of enſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his Country to a Forreign Power, and <hi>Papal Jurisdiction:</hi> whoſe Arbitrary Exactions and Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions have been ſo Intolerable, that they have been often oppos'd, and at laſt caſt off, even whilſt the Nation profeſs'd the <hi>Roman Religion.</hi> He chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to ſtand up in Vindication of the Juſt Rights, and Legal Properties of <hi>Millions</hi> of People, as much as he can, without reſiſting Lawfull Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, rather than ſuffer the Wiſe and Ancient Laws of his Country, the Freedom and Liberty of his fellow Subjects, and the True Religion eſtabliſh'd amongſt us, to become a Sacrifice and Prey to the Inveterate Rage, or inſatiable Ambition of a few
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:52620:13"/>Aſpiring and Mercileſs Men. He cannot be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that the Numerous Race of Mankind were created, on purpoſe, to be trampled upon by ſome <hi>Nero's</hi> and <hi>Caligula's,</hi> who are not contented with the Preheminence and Authority which the Laws of God, and the Land whereof they are Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, have Inveſted and Impower'd them withall: or that it is Reaſonable to think that God has gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them leave, at their Pleaſure, to dive<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t their Cruel Minds, with exerciſing the Patience and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Innocent Men, with Racks and Gibbets, and other Torments. No, as they have no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion or Authority to do Evil; ſo the Man I am ſpeaking of, looks upon himſelf in Conſcience ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged, as much as in him fairly lies, to endeavour to repreſs the Exorbitant Growth of Arbitrary Power: to ſtem the Tide of Tyranny, Superſtition, and Idolatry, when it begins to overflow the Land, and its Furious Waves attempt to undermine, and bear down the True eſtabliſh'd Religion he Profeſſes, which is dearer to him than his Life, or any Temporal Concern. For he thinks there is no juſt Reaſon to expect, that God ſhould work Miracles to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Nation</hi> from Ruin and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, when other Means may be Lawfully us'd, toward the Reſetling them upon their old Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, according to their Ancient and Legal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, without their being concern'd in Rebellion.</p>
            <p>And here I have a Fair Occaſion offer'd me, of drawing a Parallel between two Printes, who are at open Hoſtility with one another; and of ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:52620:14"/>the Juſtice of the Cauſe, in which One of them is Engaged, againſt the Unjuſt Invaſions, and Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Uſurpations of the Other. Whoſe Severe, not to ſay Inhuman Uſage of his own Faithfull and Loyal Subjects, many of whom had obliged him in the Higheſt Degree (and never diſobliged him, except when they could not comply with his Unlawful Commands) may teach us how he would deal with thoſe of another Nation, if they once ſhould be ſo Unhappy as to Groan under his Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Yoke. How would they then wiſh, and ſigh for that <hi>Deliverer</hi> which too many now ſo lightly Eſteem. If Solemn Oaths and <hi>Edicts</hi> could not bind him, from Baniſhing his own Native Subjects from their Habitations, to ſeek their Bread in For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Countreys becauſe they neither could, nor would be <hi>Papiſts,</hi> how can we, who of late, have been the Greateſt Thorn in his Side, by endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to ſtop the Progreſs of his Arms, and curb his Growing Power; who, no doubt, have exaſperated him againſt us, in a more than Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Manner, by Burning and Sinking ſome of his <hi>Capital Ships;</hi> can we I ſay, whom he looks up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as the moſt Formidable Oppoſers of his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, expect Better and more Favourable Dealings from him, than they have met with? Can we think we have obliged him as much, as his own <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Subjects have done, who ſet the Crown upon his Head? And all the World ſees how he has Requited them for it. It ſeems to me to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed either from want of due Conſideration, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a right Underſtanding of Affairs, to think that a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:52620:14"/>
               <hi>Monarch</hi> ſo much devoted to his own Intereſt, ſhould be at this Vaſt Expence of Money, and Loſs of Men, barely upon the account, of only Reaping the Naked Glory, of Reſtoring an Unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate <hi>Deſerting,</hi> and <hi>Deſerted Prince:</hi> without ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any farther Deſign. According to my ſhallow Judgement in theſe Matters, I am apt to think he had rather be a Conquerour of a Kingdom him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, than Reſtore another to it. Can we imagine he ſhould be touch'd with ſuch a feeling Senſe of Honour or Conſcience, as to impoveriſh his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and weaken his Forces for the Sake of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enthroning one Prince, when he ſhows no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern or Tenderneſs of either, in Diſpoſſeſſing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, being of his own Religion too, of their Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and Hereditary Dominions? Why ſhould not the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> the <hi>Elector Palatine,</hi> the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour,</hi> or King of <hi>Spain,</hi> be as Dear to him as ſome Body elſe? And yet I am inclin'd to believe, if he had his Will againſt the foremention'd Princes, he would leave the Glory of Reſtoring them to their Dominions to ſome other <hi>Potentate.</hi> So that I muſt beg to be excus'd, if I cannot ſubmit to the Judgement of thoſe Men, who have ſo good an Opinion of him, as to think he only Deſigns to do Juſtice, out of Pure Generoſity, by Reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the late King. And therefore I hope with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being Guilty of miſapplying my Text, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſing Scripture, I may truly ſay that our Gracious, and Righteous King <hi>William</hi> is more Excellent than This his Neighbouring Prince.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:52620:15"/>
            <p>It cannot but be Evident to a Man of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biaſs'd Judgement, that our King ſeeks to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the Publick Good; not only of theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, but of all <hi>Europe.</hi> If he could have been ſo <hi>Baſe</hi> as to have Betray'd the Liberty of his Country; or ſo <hi>Tame</hi> as only to have fat ſtill whilſt the <hi>French</hi> had overrun and ſubdu'd it, he might have made what Terms he pleas'd for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and have enjoy'd more Eaſe and Quiet than he now does. But the Safety and Welfare of his Country, of which he has been an Hereditary Defender, the Liberty of all <hi>Europe,</hi> and the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Proteſtant Religion, were Dearer to him than his own Private Intereſt and Repeſe: otherwiſe he would never have undertook ſo Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zardous an Attempt, as was that of his coming hither, to Secure and Settle the Right of his <hi>Princeſs</hi> to the Crown, by making his Appeal to a Free <hi>Parliament,</hi> and to put our disjoynted Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment into Frame and Order again, without any imaginable Probability, that He ſhould come to fill an <hi>Empty Throne.</hi> His Actions ſince his being Poſſeſs'd of theſe Kingdoms, ſufficiently ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt it to all the World, that 'twas neither Pride nor Ambition; nor love of Eaſe and Empire, that prompted him to undertake our Deliverance, and Accept the Crown. For ſince that, has he not expos'd his Life to Danger, as much, or more than ever he had done before? Has he not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergone the Greateſt Fatigues imaginable, in Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and Tedious Marches, and liv'd in a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual hurry of Buſineſs ever ſince? Men who
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:52620:15"/>only Deſign their own Profit and Advantage, give over Trading when they have acquir'd a Plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Eſtate; that they may Enjoy themſelves in Eaſe, and Pleaſure, and Quiet. They then Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire from the Noiſy Clutter of the City and Exchange, and take ſome ſatisfaction in think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how others ſcramble for that, of which they have now, with Care and Induſtry got enough: but the Acquiſition of Three Kingdoms does on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Inſpirit and Invigorate our <hi>King</hi> for Greater Undertakings; that, by the help of God, he might be the Deliverer of other <hi>Nations,</hi> as well as of theſe <hi>Kingdoms:</hi> For it is plain he does not ſo much Delight to wear a Crown as to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it. Whilſt others ſpend their flying, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Hours amidſt all the Softning Divertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Entertainments of a Splendid <hi>Court;</hi> He chuſes to tread the Rugged, but more No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Paths, which lead to True Glory and Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Honour: in ſhunning no Opportunity of ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a Gallant Army a Brave Example of Heroick Courage, and Undaunted Magnanimity, of Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Conduct, and Inimitable Valour; by too much Expoſing his Sacred Perſon to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Danger upon all Occaſions. And notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding He has never declin'd to Engage the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, upon Apparent Diſadvantage, and Une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual Number, yet the Watchfull Providence of God has Protected and Defended Him in a more than Ordinary Manner. When ſo many Inſtruments of Death have flown ſo Thick about Him, that ſome of them have gently wounded Him; yet
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:52620:16"/>none of them have had Power to touch his Life, for which extraordinary Mercy Gods holy Name be prais'd.</p>
            <p>I could willingly dwell longer upon this copious and delightfull Theme, if the Time would give me leave; but I think enough has been ſaid to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince an unprejudic'd Mind, that both <hi>He</hi> and the <hi>Cauſe</hi> in which he is engag'd are Righteous: and if ſo, it nearly concerns every True <hi>Engliſhman</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant</hi> of the Church of <hi>England</hi> to wiſh well to it, and to pray to God to proſper it with Good Succeſs; and that this War may end in a firm and laſting Peace, to the Glory of God, and the Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and Proſperity of his Church.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs, next under God, I owe my comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Subſiſtance to Him, as I believe a great many more here preſent do, and therefore I do not onely think my ſelf obliged to be inwardly gratefull and thankfull, for the Eaſe and Safety, for the Freedom and Liberty of enjoying my Religion, without Diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance; for the opportunity and pleaſure of Study, and improvement in Learning, and all the other Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of a Retired and <hi>Academick</hi> Life, which I have already enjoy'd under their <hi>Majeſties Auſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Reign;</hi> but alſo openly to teſtifie my Gratitude to others, that they may be excited to an Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of their <hi>Obligations</hi> to Him, and may be ſtirred up to pray that God would continue theſe Mercies to us, which in all likelyhood he will not long do, if we be not Thankfull for thoſe we have already receiv'd.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:52620:16"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> If the Righteous Man I am ſpeaking of, be a Private Perſon; one who is entruſted with no Power, or Authority in the Adminiſtration of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Affairs, he will be cautious and wary of being Turbulent, and Factious againſt that Government which <hi>protects</hi> him: thô he may think he finds ſome Flaws, and obſerves ſome Miſcarriages in it, or may look upon himſelf not to be obliged to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with all its Laws and Injunctions. He will not be over-haſty in Cenſuring and Condemning others, as if they had neither Reaſon nor Conſcience on their ſide, thô he cannot come up to the ſame Height of Complyance with them. A Man ought to have a care leſt he forfeit his Claim to Prudence and Diſcretion, by abounding too much in his own Senſe; and to ſuſpect leaſt his own Judgment miſguide him, when it runs <hi>counter</hi> to the Publick Laws, which are eſtabliſh'd and promulg'd by the Supreme Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, by the Concurrence and Authority of ſome of the Greateſt, and Wiſeſt, and moſt Religious Men of the Nation: and in Modeſty and Charity believe that other Men, from whom he differs in Opinion, act upon Principles of Reaſon and Conſcience as well as himſelf. So that thô it does not belong to me to condemn thoſe, who after an impartial Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the Arguments on both Sides, are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely perſuaded in their Conſciences, that they cannot Comply with Taking the <hi>Oaths;</hi> for to <hi>their own Maſter they muſt ſtand or fall,</hi> provided they demean themſelves modeſtly and peaceably, who ſubmit to it as far as they can, and do not obſtinately ſet themſelves againſt it: yet I think,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:52620:17"/>without being guilty of Cenſoriouſneſs and raſh Judging, I may condemn thoſe who are Turbulent, and Factious, and Seditious; eſpecially if they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs themſelves to be Members of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> who have all the Reaſon in the world to ſtand <hi>Neuters,</hi> at leaſt, if they think themſelves obliged not to be <hi>Actors</hi> under This Government. For certainly, however ſuch a Man may think himſelf obliged to be <hi>Paſſive</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nactive</hi> under This Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, one can ſcarcely imagin how any one, who wiſhes well to the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Nation,</hi> can let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his Humour ſo far prevail above his Reaſon, as to think himſelf bound in Conſcience to be <hi>Active</hi> in pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of it down: becauſe, in all likelyhood, our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Liberties muſt fall with it. For howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he may flatter himſelf with the Hopes of find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more than ordinary Favour under another Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution, yet, if he keeps firm to his Religion, he may chance to be deceived: But ſuppoſe he be not, but that ſome diſtinguiſhing Note of Honour, or Preferment be conferr'd upon him, for Adhering ſo ſtedfaſtly to the late K. yet, after all, he muſt be an Unnatural Son, who can rejoyce, and take Satisfaction in his Own, and a Few others Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Advancement, whileſt he beholds his <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> the Church of <hi>England</hi> depreſs'd and torn in pieces.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Righteous Man who has ſworn Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity to their Preſent <hi>Majeſties,</hi> thinks himſelf in Conſcience obliged to obſerve his Oath; becauſe he took it in Sincerity and Truth, and in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:52620:17"/>of his Heart. He did not with him men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the <hi>Tragoedian,</hi> keep his Mind unſworn whileſt he ſwore with his Tongue: but he then acted the part of an honeſt Man in Taking the Oath, as he now does in Making his Words and Actions ſutable, and conformable to what he then did. He cannot but wonder at the Indiſcretion, and Inconfiſtancy, as well as ſinfull Folly of thoſe, who having taken the Oath to <hi>K. W. and Q. M.</hi> are ſtill as much Enemies to the Preſent <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> as if they had not; and beſpatter it with more odious Reflections, and fly Inſinuations than ſome Others, who have not Sworn: this is ſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, and palpable a piece of Hypocriſie, and ſuch plain and downright Diſſimulation, that certainly thoſe Men who are Conſcious to themſelves of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Guilty this way, can never, at the ſame time, be ſo vain as to entertain any hopes of being Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in Hiſtory, for Men of Fidelity, Integrity and Honour.</p>
            <p>For whileſt they think to ſave Themſelves, by Trimming on both Sides, and to gain the Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of prudent and wary Men, they really looſe the good Eſteem of both Parties; neither of which will think it ſafe to truſt them with any Secret of Moment, or Buſineſs of Concern, for fear of being Betray'd. So that, in my Judgment, they have as little Reaſon as any to hope for Advancement, and a Favourable Reception, if the Face of Affairs, and the Scene of Government ſhould change again.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:52620:18"/>
            <p>To be firm and ſteady to a Principle we have Eſpous'd, when there is no apparent Wickedneſs in it, nor any notorious Evil and Inconvenience con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent upon it, is worthy of Praiſe and Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation. But to appear in one Dreſs to the World, and in another behind the Curtain, is to act the part of a <hi>Stage-Player,</hi> and not of a ſincere and honeſt Man. Faithfulneſs and Sincerity in our Words and Actions, in our Oaths and Promiſes, in our Bargains and Contracts, are the main Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients that compound a Righteous and Honeſt Man. Thus the Pſalmiſt in the 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>Pſalm</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing a Good Man, who is fixt upon Mount <hi>Zion,</hi> and never ſhall be moved, introduces his Character with this Queſtion, <hi>Lord who ſhall abide in thy Tabernacle? who ſhall reſt in thy Holy Hill?</hi> to which he thus replys, <hi>He that walketh upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and worketh Righteouſneſs, and ſpeaketh the Truth in his Heart, he that backbiteth not with his Tongue, nor doth Evil to his Neighbour, in whoſe eyes a Vile Perſon is contemned, but he honoureth them that fear the Lord, he that Sweareth to his own hurt and Changeth not.</hi> But perhaps, ſome may ſay, this laſt Verſe might have been more aptly apply'd to Thoſe, who refuſe to comply with the Preſent <hi>Government,</hi> upon the account of Former Oaths, taken to the late K. To which I anſwer with
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tunc enim ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſſe materiam cenſendum eſt cum rerum ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus inter tempus jurandi, &amp; tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus adimplend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta immutatus eſt, at ſi quo tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rejurabatur prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videri potuiſſet is qui peſtea in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutus eſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſtatus, non omnino juratum fuiſſet. Respon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>detur breviter, ceſſante juramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, voti, aut pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſionis materiâ ceſſare ſimul e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſdem &amp;</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligationem <hi>que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admedum in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalibus &amp; ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alibus, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiciente materi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> deficere neceſſe eſt &amp; actionem agentis, nec en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m poteſt ignis ure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, ſi deſit ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teria combuſiibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis: nec Faber, ni adſint ligna, ſcamnum facere.</hi> de Juram. Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig. <hi>Praelect.</hi> 7. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſ.</hi> 60.</note> Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> who is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd by all to be an Excellent Caſuiſt: That the Bond of an Oath is diſſolv'd, when the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of it ceaſes, or any notable Change is made concerning the Principal Cauſe of the Oath: For
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:52620:18"/>the Matter is to be thought to ceaſe, when the State of things between the Time of Swearing, and the Time of Fulfilling, is ſo chang'd, that if that ſtate of Affairs which afterwards follow'd, could have been foreſeen by him that Swore, he would not have Sworn at all. In ſhort he anſwers thus: That the Matter of an Oath, or Vow, or Promiſe cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, the <hi>Obligation</hi> to them does likewiſe ceaſe; as in Natural and Artificial things, the Matter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Deficient, there is a Neceſſity that the Action of the Agent ſhould likewiſe ceaſe. For Fire can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not burn, if there be no Combuſtible matter; nor a Carpenter make a Scaffold if he has no Wood.</p>
            <p>To conclude, the Righteous Man in this reſpect alſo excelleth his Neighbour, becauſe he prayeth for the Peace and Proſperity of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> that is, for the Safety and Welfare of the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Nation</hi> whereof he is a Member; and does not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce and triumph in the ſad Accidents and Diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, which may happen unto them, and which may tend to their Subverſion and Ruin. He looks upon it as a piece of Inhumanity not common a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the moſt Unciviliz'd People, to be devoid of all Compaſſion and Fellow-feeling toward his Countreymen, Confederates, and Fellow-Proteſtants abroad, when they ſuffer Afflictions, Loſſes and Calamities: and therefore cannot but ſtand amaz'd at the folly of thoſe, who exult with joy at their own Deſtruction, which muſt neceſſarily be involv'd in that of the whole Nation, which God of his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Mercy avert. This is as great at Inſtance of fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:52620:19"/>and indiſcretion, as if a Man ſhould rejoyce when his Neighbours houſe was on Fire, thô his own ſtood the next to be devour'd by the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching Flames. <hi>O pray for the Peace of our</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, <hi>they ſhall proſper that love her, Peace be within her Walls and Plenteouſneſs within her Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces.</hi> What remains then, but that we all aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire after thoſe things which are truly Praiſe-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy: and endeavour to excell one another in Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs and Holineſs here, that we may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd into the Habitations of Everlaſting Bliſs and Glory hereafter. Which God of his infinite Mercy grant, for <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> his ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:52620:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
